Now after that theory, let's go back to our project and this is our shop,
so this is not the rest API, this is not the graphql API,
this is the shop as we built it
and you can find this snapshot of it attached to this lecture. Now in there,
let's first of all explore that environment variables thing I was talking about and we can start in the
app.js file, what would we control in an environment variable
and what is an environment variable? Now environment variables are a concept supported by nodejs where
we can pass certain configurations, certain values into our node application from outside,
so we don't hardcode certain values into our node code,
instead the values will be injected when our node server starts and that allows us to use different
values in development and production and also to conveniently change the values in production without
having to redeploy our entire code.
And a great example can already be seen here, that connection string here. This connection string allows
us to connect to our mongoose cluster
and obviously we have some hardcoded values here,
the username and the password for this user
and then also the default database. If we want to change anything there,
well then we have to change it in the code and redeploy it.
Additionally if we ever share this code with someone, like I do with you, you know these credentials. Now
they won't matter much to you because I change my password after I quit recording this course but of
course in a real application, you can't change your passwords every time you share the code with some
coworker or anything like that and therefore you want to use node environment variables here.
Another place where we would want to use one is at the bottom of this file, here where we set the port
where this should start. In development, we use 3000
and we can basically use any number that is above the thousand range but in production, we want
to let our server or our hosting provider set this port because that is in the end the thing,
the service that does open our app to the web and that does configure all the network settings,
so there we don't control the port number but the hosting provider does.
Another example for something we want to control in an environment variable can be found in the shop
controller. There at the top,
I have this stripe key,
not only is this the development key which we have to exchange for the production key but it's also
not a good idea to hardcode it in here for the same reasons as it was with our mongoose data.
So let's use some environment variables and using them is straightforward.
Now first of all, I'll turn this connection url into a template literal by replacing the single
quotation marks with back ticks.
Now it's still a normal string but now we can inject values by using dollar sign curly braces
and now here, we can access environments variables on the process object, this is an object not defined by us
but this is globally available in the node app,
it's part of the node core runtime.
Now on this process object, we have the very helpful env property and that is now an object with all the
environment variables
this node process knows. There are a bunch of default environment variables but we can also set our own
ones
and here let's say I want to use the mongo user environment variable and I'll replace this text with
it.
Now I also want to replace the password,
so here I'll use mongo password
and I'll remove the password here and I will show you how to set these environment variables in a second
of course. The database here, we can also replace that with mongo default database,
alternatively you could of course make that whole connection string an environment variable depending
on whether that string changes regularly or just the values inside of it.
Regarding the port, I'll also go down and here instead of setting 3000, I'll set process env port or if that
should be undefined, 3000.
Now most hosting providers or all hosting providers that manage that for us will automatically inject the
port environment variable,
so most of the time we can rely on that being set and for local development, we'll still fallback to
3000 because there, it will not be set. Now for stripe,
if I move to the shop controller, I also want to use an environment variable here
and I will use process env stripe key here.
With that I replaced a couple of things with environment variables where it makes sense.
Now if you scroll through all the code, you might find other occasions where you would say ok I want to set
that from outside,
I don't want to hardcode that but these things which I now exchanged are definitely important ones.
Now we do try to read these environment variables in our node code,
how can we now pass them into node? Well we do that when we run our node application, with nodemon, we
can provide a configuration file.
You can simply add a nodemon.json file in your project root folder and there, provide a json document,
opening and closing curly braces. In there, add an env
object
and there you can now set your environment variables like mongo user, there the value should be Maximillian
mongo password,
so all these variables I tried to read in my code and that should be the password
you just well removed from your app.js
file
and also mongo database and there
I will now use shop like this.
So now I added the environment variables for my mongodb connection string here and that should be named
mongo default database I see so let's rename it here too
and besides these mongo things here, we could set the port
but there we have a default value, after the two pipe symbols
we always fallback to 3000.
Now for stripe, we also want to inject something and there we should sign into our dashboard and in that
dashboard, go to developers API keys.
Now here for the server, you will need that secret key and you want to move that into your nodemon package,
so there I named the environment variable stripe key and that is how I should name it here too, so that
would be the value.
And now that if you run npm start, it should still start and it should still connect,
I get an error that mongo default database is not defined because of course here in the connection string,
it should should be process env mongo default database just as it is in all the other places.
Thereafter everything starts just fine
and now we have a running application using these environment variables.
Now these are still the development values but nonetheless we have that set up.
Now of course we're not always using nodemon and especially when deploying this app, we'll not be using it
because there we don't
want to restart the server on every change because we will not change the code anyways. So what I'll do
is I'll add a new start script to my package.json file,
I'll name it
start:dev,
you can name it however you want,
you could just name it dev, whatever you want
and there I will use nodemon and in my main start strip,
I just want to use node.
This however will now not use the nodemon.json file.
So if you want to pass an environment variables here, you also got different solutions
and typically when using a hosting provider, you can set up the environment variables in the dashboard
of your hosting provider,
that is something we'll see later
but if you're not using that, well then you can
as a simple solution simply take the key value pairs you want to set up and add them in your package.json
file in front of the start script.
So there you would use mongo user equals Maximillian, like this
and you would do that for all the values you want to pass in.
So now we can do the same for the password, mongo password, you simply separate it with a whitespace, mongo
password
equals this mongo default database equals shop and the stripe
key equals
and now I need to get that stripe key here,
copy that, move it here and now we are obviously a very long startup string.
Again typically we'll not pass it like this but now if I would run npm start it should still start and
connect without issues to the mongodb database
because now we are running this with our environment variables here.
I also want to highlight one special environment variable which you can set manually and that is a
special one which I just want to log here, on process env there is the node env variable
and now if I quit my server and restart it, you see undefined here.
Now again this will be set automatically by hosting providers,
you can of course also set it on your own and hosting providers will set this to production.
Now if I restart, we see production being logged here and this is a special environment variable even
though it's not set by default because expressjs will actually use that by default to determine
the environment mode and if you set that to production, expressjs will change certain things
and for example, it will reduce the details for errors
it throws and in general, optimize some things for deployment.
So you want to set those when running your app in production
and again hosting providers typically do that for you.
You can always check out the official docs of your favorite hosting provider to find out if that is the
case.